Wharton mss., 1836-1975 (bulk 1900-1937) LMC 2073
Lilly Library
Wharton mss.
1836-1975
Lilly Library
Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937
Tyler, William Royall, 1910-
Tyler, Elisina, 1875-1959.
Berenson, Bernard, 1865-1959.
Tyler, Royall.
Berenson, Mary, 1864-1945
Bourget, Paul, 1852-1935.
Bromfield, Louis, 1896-1956.
Clark, Kenneth, 1903-1983
Cortissoz, Royal, 1869-1948.
Farrand, Beatrix, 1872-1959.
Gerhardie, William Alexander, 1895-1977
Gillet, Louis, 1876-1943.
Mugnier, abbé (Arthur), 1853-1944.
Lee, Vernon, 1856-1935.
Sheldon, Edward, 1886-1946.
Smith, Logan Pearsall, 1865-1946.
Fullerton, William Morton, b. 1865.
LMC 2073
6 Boxes 3 standard; 3 phase boxes
The Wharton mss., 1836-1975 (bulk 1900-1937), consists of the correspondence, diaries, and writings of novelist Edith Newbold Jones Wharton, 1862-1937.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 1976
Biographical Note
Edith Newbold Jones Wharton, 1862-1937, was an American novelist. She was born on January 24, 1862 in New York City, the daughter of George Frederic Jones and his wife Lucretia Rhinelander. She began writing at an early age: Verses, a volume of her poems, was published privately when Wharton was 16. She made her debut into society in 1879, participating in the various parties and social events of upper class New York. After an unsuccessful engagement to Henry Leyden Stevens, Wharton married Edward Robbins (Teddy) Wharton on April 29, 1885. She spent her early marriage decorating her various homes and traveling frequently to Europe with her husband. The couple moved to Lenox, Massachusetts in 1902 and established their estate known as The Mount where they would live until 1911. Wharton designed both the interiors and gardens of The Mount according to the principles she had set forth in her first published book, The Decoration of Houses (1897). She also used her time at The Mount to write two of her most famous novels: The House of Mirth (1905) and Ethan Frome (1911).
After divorcing her husband in 1913, Wharton moved to France, where she would live for the duration of World War I. In 1916, Wharton was awarded the French Legion of Honor for her work with charitable and humanitarian causes during the war. At the end of the war, she acquired two new homes: Pavillon Colombe (a villa in Saint-Brice-sous-Forêt) and Sainte-Claire du Château (a restored convent in Hyères). Wharton's novel The Age of Innocence (1920) won the Pulitzer Prize for Fiction in 1921, making her the first woman to do so. She spent the remainder of her life in France, dying on August 11, 1937 at Pavillon Colombe.
Scope and Content Note
The earliest items in the collection are family related: a commonplace book of Wharton's mother, Lucretia Rhinelander, and an 1847 journal of Wharton's father, George Frederic Jones. The correspondence begins in 1901 and includes letters from Bernard Berenson, Mary (Smith) Berenson, Paul Bourget, Louis Bromfield, Sir Kenneth Clark, Royal Cortissoz, Beatrix Farrand, William Alexander Gerhardie, Louis Gillet, Abbé Arthur Mugnier, Violet Paget, Edward Brewster Sheldon, Logan Pearsall Smith, Elisina Tyler, Royall Tyler, and William Royal Tyler, as well as nearly 400 letters from Edith Wharton to the Tyler family. Her own diaries cover primarily 1920-1937, but also present is the so-called "love diary" (A Life Apart) of 1907-08. Writings present include typescripts of her full-length works (Age of Innocence, A Backward Glance, and Gods Arrive) as well as many poems both published and unpublished. A file of about two hundred photographs of Wharton and friends, of Pavillon Colombe, of Saint Claire Château, and of her other residences (The Mount, Pencraig, and 58 rue de Varenne) complete this portion of the collection.
The remaining portion of the collection consists of files relating to Edith Wharton's death and her estate, as well as correspondence and other materials gathered by the executor of her French will, Elisina Tyler, for a planned biography of Wharton. The biography was never completed, and following Elisina's death in 1959, her son, William Royall Tyler, took over as executor of the Wharton estate. His correspondence as well as some additional materials relating to his own reminiscences of Mrs. Wharton, complete the entire collection. Among the correspondents in this Wharton/Tyler portion of the collection are William Morton Fullerton, William Alexander Gerhardie, Frederic Rhinelander King, John Hugh Smith, Elisina Tyler, William Royall Tyler, Emelyn Webster Washburn, and Armitage Watkins.
All of this material was consulted and used by R.W.B. Lewis in his volume Edith Wharton: A Biography (New York: Harper & Row, 1975) and is described and cited there as the William Royall Tyler Collection, Dumbarton Oaks, Washington, DC.
Note on Indexing Term - "World War, 1914-1918": During World War I when she was living in France, Wharton became involved in various philanthropic activities and there is some material in the collection concerning these activities.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into family-related items, correspondence, writings, and files relating to Edith Wharton's death and estate.
Women; World War, 1914-1918; Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937.; Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937 --Correspondence.; Authors, American --Correspondence.
- Letters to Edith Wharton (Box 1)
  - Bernard Berenson, 1928-1936; (14 folders) (Box 1)
  - William Gerhardie, 1922-1931; (1 folder) (Box 1)
- Letters to EW, 1900-1937; (11 folders) (Box 1)
- Letters from EW, 1917-1937; (4 items) (Box 1)
- Letters from EW to the Tyler family (Box 1)
  - Elisina, 1914-1937; (8 folders) (Box 1)
  - Royall Tyler, 1918-1935; (17 items) (Box 1)
  - William Royall Tyler, 1923-1937; (1 folder) (Box 1)
- Diaries, EW, (7 vols.) (Box 1)
- Diaries, not EW (Box 2)
  - Lucretia Rhinelander, 1836-1840 (Box 2)
    General
    [commonplace book]
  - George Frederic Jones, Apr. 7, 1847-June 1, 1848 (Box 2)
    [diary]
- Writings by EW (Box 2)
  - Age of Innocence T.D. (Age of Innocence)
  - A Backward Glance T.D. (A Backward Glance)
  - Beaumetz T.D., February 23rd 1915; 2p. (Box 2)
  - The Bitter End A.D., incomplete (Box 2)
  - The Buccaneers T.D. (Box 2)
  - Derivation of the word cant A.D. and T.D. (Box 2)
  - Easter A.D. and T.D. (Box 2)
  - Fast and Loose. A Novelette by David Olivieri. photocopy of ms.; T.D., 59p. (Box 2)
  - Fast and Loose [imaginary reviews] A.D. and T.D. (Box 2)
  - Freeman is "perfectly lovely" or "quite too lovely"... [1st line] T.D., 1p. (Box 2)
  - The Gods Arrive. bound typescript (The Gods Arrive)
  - Hope. holograph (Box 2)
  - In this world.... typescript (Box 2)
  - Literary Tendencies. holograph in notebook with autobiographical fragments (Box 2)
  - Memories (summary). typescript (Box 2)
  - Misc. & fragments. holograph (Box 2)
  - The Mummy Room. incomplete holograph and typescript (Box 2)
  - My Books - Literary Essays. holograph and typescript (Box 2)
  - Notebook holograph, 1, April 1914 (Box 2)
  - Notebook 2: [poems] holograph (Box 2)
    - The Southwind (Box 2)
    - The Northwind (Box 2)
    - The new Litany (Box 2)
    - Song (Let us be lovers...) (Box 2)
    - Song (Mirth of life's blooming-time...) (Box 2)
    - The Rose (Box 2)
    - Weltschmerz (Box 2)
    - Phyllis (Box 2)
    - Death (Box 2)
    - Gifts (Box 2)
    - The Inferno (Box 2)
    - Beauty (Box 2)
    - Swinburne (Box 2)
    - A Patient Soul (Box 2)
    - The Sonnet's Boundaries (Box 2)
    - A Vision (Box 2)
    - Esther (Box 2)
    - Ante-Mortem (Box 2)
    - The So-Called Venus of Milo (Box 2)
    - Lucrezia Buonvisi's Lover (Dying at Vareggion) (?) (Box 2)
    - Dactylics (Box 2)
    - The Masque of Life (Box 2)
    - Dante (Box 2)
    - The Old Odysseus (Box 2)
    - Mindest Thou no more? (Box 2)
    - The Duchess of Palliano (Box 2)
    - The Dead Wife (Box 2)
    - Demeter (Box 2)
    - October in Newport (Box 2)
    - In the Forest (Box 2)
    - The Tomb of Ilaria Giunigi (Box 2)
    - Terza Rima (Box 2)
    - Sapphics (Box 2)
    - Renunciation (Box 2)
    - Latomia dei Cappucini (Box 2)
    - Cor Cordium (Box 2)
    - A Dialogue (Box 2)
    - The Leper's Funeral and Death (In mediaeval England) (Box 2)
    - Beaulieu Wood (Box 2)
    - Browsing in the Abbey (Box 2)
    - Cynthia (Box 2)
    - From "The New and the Old" (Box 2)
    - Friends (Box 2)
    - Lucrezia Buonvisi Remembers (Box 2)
    - Life (Box 2)
    - An Autumn Day (Box 2)
    - Lines for "Boulterby Ridge" (Box 2)
    - Life (Box 2)
    - Song (Box 2)
    - Cinque Cents (Box 2)
    - The 'Beata Beatrix' of Rossetti (Box 2)
    - Hymn to Colom (Box 2)
  - Ogrin the Hermit. holograph and typescript (Box 2)
  - Penelope. typescript (Box 2)
  - A Princess of the House of Este. holograph (Box 2)
  - The so-called Venus of Milo. holograph (Box 2)
  - Treasure. holograph (Box 2)
  - With the Tide. holograph (Box 2)
  - Printed [poems - 2 items] (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Identity and travel papers, 1914-1937 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - [inventory of Walter Berry's library] (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - "Mademoiselle Colombe l'..." A.D. 11p. In French. on verso" History of Pavillon Colombe & des soeurs Colombe" (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Notes, fragments, lists, etc. [some are in Wharton's hand] (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - [Proust,] Marcel. "Response a une question: Léon Radziwill" T(carbon) D., 3p. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - recipes (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Rhinelander: "Our debt to Britain." printed [a memorial service address], 1918 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - [Sketchbook] (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Printed articles, etc., by or relating to EW (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - clippings: by or about EW [see also folio] (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - clippings: miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Elisina Tyler files (Box 2)
  - Tyler, E. correspondence, 1919-1954 (Box 11, Folder 1-8)
  - typed transcripts of Wharton's letters to Edward Sheldon (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - miscellaneous re: Wharton estate, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - miscellaneous notes, extracts, etc. re: Wharton (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - "Outline for proposed interview with Mrs. Royall Tyler" T.(carbon)D., 1919; 6p. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - 1925. Edith Wharton by R.M. Lovett [photocopy] (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - [E. Tyler account of EW's last illness and death] T.D. 34p. heavily annotated in ink; T(carbon), 1937, June 11-Aug. 7; 34p. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - EW obituaries - clippings, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - June. E. Tyler: "Statement concerning...Mrs. Wharton's last illness and of the execution of her last will and testament." T.D. 19p. with handwritten changes and corrections; T(carbon)., 1939; 34p. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Wilson, Edmund "Edith Wharton: A Memoir by an English Friend.: T.D., 5p.; T(carbon), [1949]; 5p. (Box 12, Folder 6)
- William Royall Tyler files (Box 2)
  - Tyler, W.R. correspondence, 1947-1975 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - correspondence with and about William Gerhardie, 1971-1974 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - "Transcripts of tapes recorded...summer by W.R.T. from E.R.T. correspondence and documents, mostly concerning E.W." T.D., 1972 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - [extracts from various E.W. or E.T. letters, etc.] (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Photographs (Box 3)
  - Drawing of EW, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of EW (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of others (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs used in Lewis biography (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Proofs from Lewis biography (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Pavilion Colombe (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of The Mount, Pencraig and 58 rue de Varenne (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Ste. Claire (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous snapshots (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Negatives (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Watercolor drawing (Box 3, Folder 12)